<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-08T13:38:20+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Randall Moeller</title><subtitle>&lt;strong&gt;Welcome to the New Frontier&lt;/strong&gt;</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why You Should Hit That Subscribe Button (to the Upper Right)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/welcome" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why You Should Hit That Subscribe Button (to the Upper Right)" /><published>2020-05-07T18:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T18:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/welcome">&lt;p&gt;My Substack will be awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subscribe to it &lt;a href=&quot;https://randallmoeller.substack.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Randall Moeller</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">My Substack will be awesome.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Try My Podcast, “Blocks of Wisdom”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/podcast" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Try My Podcast, &quot;Blocks of Wisdom&quot;" /><published>2020-05-07T17:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T17:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/podcast</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/podcast">My podcast will be great.</content><author><name>Randall Moeller</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">My podcast will be great.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Is Where to Get Cool Stuff</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/store" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Is Where to Get Cool Stuff" /><published>2020-05-07T16:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T16:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/store</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/store">OK, I haven't made anything yet, but when I do, it will go here.</content><author><name>Randall Moeller</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">OK, I haven't made anything yet, but when I do, it will go here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I.T.P. (Imaginary Theme Park)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/itp" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I.T.P. (Imaginary Theme Park)" /><published>2020-05-07T15:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-05-07T15:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/itp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/itp">Here goes my imaginary theme park!</content><author><name>Randall Moeller</name></author><category term="Getting started" /><summary type="html">Here goes my imaginary theme park!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taiwan Culture Test</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/taiwan-culture-test" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taiwan Culture Test" /><published>2020-05-06T18:18:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-05-06T18:18:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/taiwan-culture-test</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/taiwan-culture-test">&lt;p&gt;At my friend Miaca’s Kuantum Cafe – a lovely place in Taipei that’s since closed – we used to have a book club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one night we decided to write up a Taiwan Culture Test, in homage to the various “culture tests” posted at zompist.com. Here’s the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;If you’re Taiwanese…&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You believe that there are different gods for different purposes, and worship them at different times for different things.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You may be superstitious or believe in Feng Shui. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’re familiar with May Day, Jolin Tsai, Jay Chou, James Xiao, Ang Lee, YoYo Ma, Jeremy Lin, Jian Ming Wang (Chien Ming), Amei Zhang Hui Mei, Kang Xi Lai Le, “Cape Number 7”, Hou Xiao Xian, Yani Tseng, Jiang Hui, “You are the apple of my eye”, Pi Li Huo (PiLi Fire), and Taiwanese Tornado. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You know how baseball is played. Thanks to Linsanity, you may know the rules of basketball as well.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You count yourself fortunate if you get two weeks of vacation a year. One of them will be for Chinese New Year in January or February. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You think it’s way better to be a boss than an employee. The boss controls everything. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You think that your salary is way too low because it never increases. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are used to earthquakes by now. Also typhoons. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You know how to ride a scooter. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You wonder why people can’t understand the difference between your country and Thailand. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must know “bopomofo” (a uniquely Taiwanese phonetic writing system) and maybe you know how to type in Chinese with the “boshiyami”, “hanglie”, “cangjie” and/or “dayi” input methods. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t curl your tongue when you speak – if you’re flying in from Beijing, drop the R’s. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are not satisfied with the generous social welfare, free wifi everywhere and the low cost of living, but always wish to go overseas.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Have you eaten yet?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You know there’s something to eat anywhere, any time. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You love the soup dumplings, but not only at Din Tai Fung (a perennial tourist favorite). &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You love the mango shaved ice at local places, but not necessarily at the expensive Ice Monster (another tourist favorite). &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ve often been to night markets to sample local delights - such as beef noodles, Taiwanese Fried Chicken (#1 late-night snack), meat sausage in rice sausage, stinky tofu, braised pork rice (lu rou fan - 魯肉飯), oyster omelette, pig blood cake, and fried chicken fillet. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You may be highly nutrition-conscious. Maybe you take vitamins and you believe in organic products. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’re used to having cafes in every alley, many of which roast their own beans. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are proud to live in the place where bubble tea (pearl milk tea) was invented. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are proud to be in the country that grows high quality tea, produces the best fruits in Asia. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Late at night, if you’re feeling hungry, you go to the local soy milk breakfast shop for delicious snacks like fried bread sticks (you tiao), scallion pancakes (cong you bing), or fried dumplings (guo tie), or you order the Taiwanese Fried Chicken from that little booth near your house, or you go for congee and Taiwanese dishes, or the cold noodle and meatball soup. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have to eat while you drink so you can drink more…there’s not much of a pub culture, though. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must have been to the $100 NT (New Taiwanese dollar) hot fry dish restaurant and enjoy the super high volume shouting around you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;A Chinese-speaking democracy&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are proud to live in a country where different political parties win elections. Since 1996, there have been four presidents, two each from two opposing parties. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You probably know exactly which side of the political fence you stand on (“green” for the DPP or “blue” for the KMT). &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re old enough, you may have thrown peanuts on the ground and angrily stomped on them when U.S. president Jimmy Carter stopped recognizing Taiwan as a country and began diplomatic relations with the People’s Republic of China instead. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’re used to a complicated system where most countries have “institutes” or “trade offices” in your country instead of embassies. Your country’s athletes have to wear “Chinese Taipei” uniforms during international competitions to avoid upsetting the mainlanders. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re a man, you spent a year doing military service, but it wasn’t as intense as it is in some other countries, and you even got paid while you served.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The way things work&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s a 7-11 or Family Mart (sometimes both) on nearly every block. You can do almost everything there 24 hours a day – buy groceries, eat a meal, pay your bills, print out documents, receive packages, buy concert tickets, and so on. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scooters, scooters everywhere. And not too many sidewalks. If you’re a pedestrian, you learn fast to get out of the way. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can buy almost anything online, and delivery is fast. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You take your excellent health care system for granted. You like to visit hospitals and enjoy your social insurance benefits any time you get the chance. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At night, when you hear a truck outside playing Beethoven’s “For Elise”, you know it’s time to run out and throw your garbage bags into the truck. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You know that multicolored blinking lights in the shape of a fan mean there’s a betel nut stand just below the sign. People buy the nuts, chew them, and then spit out red saliva. Betel nut stands by the highway are staffed by cute girls in bikinis, especially in Southern Taiwan. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You read Chinese in traditional characters, not the simplified characters they use on the mainland. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’re used to an excellent public transportation system, with high-speed rail connecting much of the island, and ubiquitous bikes available for rent. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must know what PTT is and know how to use it. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You always look forward to the year-end party and the chance of winning the lucky draw, also the big bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mind your manners&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’ve had to study English since elementary school, day and night. So your English is probably good. But you still tell everyone that your English is terrible, and are afraid to speak it. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You always line up.  In fact, you love to line up SO MUCH that if you see a line outside a store, you will probably get in it. You prefer the stores and restaurants that have lines outside them. You think it will never be wrong. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are honest. You expect that if you forget something somewhere, you will be able to return later and find it untouched, just where you left it. But when you travel outside Taiwan, you may get a shock when you leave your laptop unattended in a cafe. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You expect to be safe 24/7 just about anywhere. You can walk down a dark street late at night without fear. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You value people more than laws. You try to figure out how to get along with people without involving lawyers. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You value following the crowd and fitting in. You must take your selfie just like everyone else at the “infamous” spots. Don’t forget to make the obligatory peace sign! &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You’re probably not always punctual. If you’re meeting someone you know, it’s not unheard-of for you to be 15 or even 30 minutes late. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There sure are a lot of meetings at your office. They seem endless and nothing ever gets done. Almost no one speaks during the meeting but everyone talks after it. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Around the neighborhood&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All your friends from other Asian countries, such as Hong Kong, Singapore, want to move to Taiwan for retirement. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But you don’t visit Hong Kong often, and you may never have gone at all, even though it’s an hour’s flight away. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You love Japan and Japanese culture. You live in the only former Japanese colony where the locals got along well with the Japanese. Japan is your #1 choice for foreign travel. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You love K-pop idols but you hate Korean sports stars. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you meet an American, he’s probably here to teach English.
 &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mountains, mountains and mountains, we have many mountains in Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Randall Moeller</name></author><category term="fables" /><summary type="html">At my friend Miaca’s Kuantum Cafe – a lovely place in Taipei that’s since closed – we used to have a book club.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Importance of Sucking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sucking" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Importance of Sucking" /><published>2020-05-06T18:18:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-05-06T18:18:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sucking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sucking">&lt;p&gt;I may know a little about this&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Randall Moeller</name></author><category term="speeches" /><summary type="html">I may know a little about this</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Salsa in Taipei</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/salsa" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Salsa in Taipei" /><published>2020-05-06T18:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-05-06T18:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/salsa</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/salsa">Lorem salsam boogie woogie</content><author><name>Randall Moeller</name></author><summary type="html">Lorem salsam boogie woogie</summary></entry></feed>